A SWORDSMAN OF MARS

by Lin Carter

THE MYSTERIOUS MESSAGE

During July and August, when the heat and humidity make living in the city somewhat less than pleasant, I am accustomed to renting a cabin in the woods around Lake Carlopa in upstate New York. I simply carry along food and cigarettes, plenty of books to read, and my favorite dog, a bull terrier named McGurk. We explore the woods and swim in the lake, and enjoy the rustic solitude and the scenery, which is spectacular.

The nights grow chilly, regardless of the month, so after dinner I build a fire in the big fieldstone fireplace and stretch out with a book, while Gurk basks on the hearth, dreaming his doggy dreams.

On this particular occasion I had brought along several new books I had not yet read, and a few old friends with whom I wished to familiarize myself again—Jack Williamson’s Legion of Time, Van Vogt’s The Book of Ptath, Dodie Smith’s I Capture the Castle, and some volumes of verse.

On the night it happened, July 17th, I had been browsing through the verses of one of the most interesting of all the poets of the East, the Syrian poet Abu’l-Ala, who wrote his lovely and haunting quatrains in the last years of the tenth century, a generation before the birth of Omar Khayyam, whom he so much resembles. In his quatrains he examines the claims of religion and mysticism and explores the mysteries of life and death and of the life beyond. I remember being struck by two quatrains in particular, these two:

Myself did linger by the ragged beach,
Whereat wave after wave did rise and curl;
And as they fell, they fell—I saw them hurl
A message far more eloquent than speech:
‘We that with song our pilgrimage beguile,
With purple islands which a sunset bore,
We, sunk upon the sacrilegious shore,
May parley with oblivion awhile.’

I cannot explain why, but those lines stirred profound depths of thought within me. I took up the yellow ruled tablet I keep close to hand when reading in case I wish to make a note or jot down a quotation for future use, and the pen that lay beside it. These I rested against my knee, and, with uncapped pen in hand, fell into a somber reverie.

My body was utterly relaxed, my mind clear and lucid but deep in thought. Then there fell over me something strange and eerie, a trance-like state, a waking dream. For I was wide awake and fully aware of my surroundings. I could hear the ticking of the clock on the mantelpiece, the rustling of leaves in the wind, the crackling of the fire, the whines of my dog as he chased rabbits in his dream.

Without volition, my hand began to move rapidly across the page of the tablet, inditing line after line in a neat, tight script very very unlike my own ungainly scrawl. I was aware of this but it neither frightened nor concerned me. Page after page of handwriting followed in this manner.

Two hours later, or a bit more, I aroused myself from this weird trance, drenched in perspiration and shaking with exhaustion, my right hand and arm numb and trembling from strain. I got up and went to bed, falling at once into a deep and dreamless sleep from which I awoke the next morning, rested and refreshed. Only then, over a hearty breakfast of scrambled eggs and Canadian bacon and buttered toast, did I read what my hand had written.

It was the opening pages of the book you are holding at this moment, four or five thousand words of clear, legible handwriting in a hand not my own.

I have no explanation for this, nor do I really expect anyone to believe me. The phenomenon is well known, and a copious literature exists upon it. It is called automatic writing. The psychologists have one explanation for it, involving the creative powers of the subconscious mind; the occultists and spiritualists have another, concerning communications by disembodied spirits in the next life.

I have no explanation to offer, and cannot quite accept either of the alternative answers given by science and religion.

Night after night thereafter, at the same time, again there came upon me that uncanny waking sleep, and each morning more and more of the narrative had written itself.

To this account, I have but one more thing to add. My friend Dr. Kenneth Franklin, the astronomer in residence at New York’s famous Hayden Planetarium, told me in answer to my question that the fourteen days beginning on the night of July 17th are the period of the year when the planet Mars comes closest to the Earth.

—LIN CARTER

Chapter I

On Another World

My name is Jad Tedron, dator or prince of Zorad on the planet you call Mars, but which we who roam its dying surface know by the name of Barsoom.

But I was not born Jad Tedron and neither is Zorad truly the city of my birth. My story is a strange one and may indeed be unique in the annals of human experience, for aught I know. I have encountered many mysteries in my life upon the Red Planet which no one can readily explain, and I least of all. But I shall narrate here the tale of my adventure as best I can, confident in the knowledge that no one can do any better than his best . . .

To begin, then: I was born in a town called Logansville in the Texas panhandle. My father, Matthew Dexter, was a physician who moved to this town after graduating from a small medical school in St. Louis. Here he met and came to love the woman who, in time, became my mother. She was a lovely, gracious woman, the daughter of the town banker, but as she died in introducing me into this world, I am afraid that all my memories of her are merely second-hand.

My father’s practice ranged over a hundred square miles of arid, sun-baked prairie, and very often I did not see him from dawn to dusk, and in lieu of any other playmate I was forced to amuse myself not only by inventing my own games but also a host of imaginary playmates to enjoy them with.

These were lonely years, as you can imagine, but they were happy years as well. We were not poor, since my mother had inherited a comfortable income from my banker grandfather. Just before my high school graduation, however, there came upon us that phenomenon known as the Great Depression, and the doors of the Logansville bank closed forever upon the stocks and bonds my grandfather had so assiduously gathered for all those years. At one stroke my father was made penniless, and gone were all his dreams of sending me to college and then, perhaps, on to medical school, so that I might carry on in his footsteps in the practice of that profession which has always seemed to me the noblest and most useful of any known to man, the healing of sickness, the comforting of the ill or injured.

I found a job as a roustabout with a small, rundown traveling circus which carried me, in the years that followed, the length and breadth of Texas and Oklahoma and even Kansas. This unlikely profession was not one of my choosing, but I soon came to love the cheap, garish, carefree life of the circus, and with my strapping inches and rugged physique, it was a profession for which nature, if not inclination, had ably prepared me.

My father never quite recovered from the loss of his fortunes, and although I weekly sent home what few dollars I could spare from my meagre earnings, he began to fail, it was not so much a matter of bodily health, for he had always been robust and hearty, with the stamina of two men, as it was the results of the black mood of melancholy and the feeling that life itself had defeated him. He died soon after my twenty-first birthday. I made my last trip home to the small town which had nurtured me in my boyhood, to bury him . . .

He sleeps forever under the green sod of the small country church beside my mother. God bless them both, and may their eternal sleep ever be bright with joyous dreams.

The demise of my father having severed the last remaining link with the town of my birth, I resolved to travel and to see as much of the world as a man of slender means may do. I soon joined Caulfield's Flying Circus, a traveling air show which barnstormed the prairies of the great southwest, first as a mechanic and later as a stunt pilot. For I discovered that I possessed a natural talent for tinkering with machinery and an utter fearlessness of flying, both of which talents go into the making of a born aviator.

But it is not my intention to relate here the fairly exciting but basically routine life of Thad Dexter, daredevil stunt flyer, barnstorming pilot and vagabond aviator. For that life was cut cruelly short before I was thirty, during a stunt flight at a country fair in the fields outside of Baxter, Wyoming, when my parachute failed to open until it was too late to do more than barely break my fall.

That I survived that disaster, even for half an hour, is probably due to the iron strength and tireless endurance I inherited from my hardy pioneer forebears. But I did not survive for long; too many bones were broken and my flesh too terribly mangled for nature or medicine to knit.

My last sight was the worn, tired, kindly face of a country doctor whose name I shall never know, as he bent over me, murmuring quiet words of comfort. That, and a strangely prophetic glimpse through a window in the crude little one-room surgery to which the townsfolk had borne me.

For just as the odor of chloroform filled my lungs and blotted out the consciousness of Thad Dexter forever—as one would have thought— I saw beckoning like a bright beacon through the nighted skies that arched above the dusty plains of Wyoming that distant, ruddy spark that was the Red Planet, Mars, the planet of mystery.

For some reason, that red star caught and held my fading consciousness and I clung to the sight of it, blazing like the eternal enigma it is through the dark skies, until at last my consciousness ebbed and died like a candle blown in the wind.

I died there on the operating table; I know this beyond all doubt or question. But I was reborn to live again in another life on a distant world ... and that is the first of the mysteries in my story which I shall not even attempt to explain, for they have no explanation.

I had been raised in the simple faith of my mother, but my father instilled in me from my earliest years a healthy scepticism of all who pretend to be able to interpret the unknown secrets of life and death and of the world beyond. It was my father's opinion, which I came later to share, that no man can honestly claim to know for certain anything of heaven or the afterlife or the inscrutable will of God, and that all doctrines and dogmas are shallow and ultimately futile attempts to persuade the gullible otherwise.

And if I took my simple childhood faith with a grain or two of salt, you may imagine what little credence I placed in the foreign religions of alien lands. Such outlandish creeds as reincarnation and metempsychosis or the Pythagorean concept of the transmigration of souls I deemed little more than fanciful whimsies born of the fertile imagination of the East.

There was, therefore, no theory by which I could rationalize or explain, even to my own inner satisfaction, the incredible fact of my rebirth upon another planet which followed upon the termination of my earthly existence on that operating table, of which my last living memories are so clear and unequivocal. Do the dead of our world go into their graves upon this earth, to rise reborn upon the dead seabottoms of ancient and mysterious Mars? If so, in all the span of my second life upon the Red Planet, I have never met another man or woman who could recall their previous life on Earth (or Jasoom, as they call it) as can I.

Do I truly live upon this strange world amidst its myriad marvels, which floats in the vast abyss of heaven forty-three million miles from my native world, or is this second life naught more than an indefinitely prolonged and amazingly vivid dream born in the dying brain of an injured aviator, clinging desperately to the feeble and faint and flickering spark of life? Or was my former life on Earth the dream, and this strange life on Barsoom the true and only reality?

I can give you the answers to none of these questions, alas. Nor can any priest or mystic or philosopher, I somehow feel certain.

But following the rude termination of my earthly life, I was born again on distant Mars in the city of Zorad which lies in the northern hemisphere of the Red Planet, on a forested plateau which was once, untold millions of years before, an island in the midst of the Xanthus, the smallest of the five oceans of ancient Mars. These oceans, the greatest of which was the mighty Throxeus in the southern hemisphere of the planet, have long since dwindled away over the inexorable passage of the ages, and at the time of my advent upon this world all of them had vanished, leaving behind only the dead seabottoms carpeted with rust-red sands broken only by those long zones of ochre moss which the Martians cultivate for food and to produce oxygen which serves to continuously replenish their thin atmosphere.

Once long ago over these ruddy plains the pounding billows of mighty oceans drove, but one by one the seas gradually receded, their waters evaporating into the weirdly purple skies of Mars, as the old planet aged and began to die, save perhaps for the legendary Lost Sea of Korus which the Martians suppose to exist in the regions of their South Pole, and which may or may not exist in actuality.

The more civilized of the inhabitants of Mars are human in every aspect, save perhaps in their remarkable longevity and in the mysterious power of telepathy which they possess and which enables them to read the thoughts of others or to project their own mental communications over remarkable distances, or to communicate to some degree even with the minds of the curious beasts with which they share their weird world. As for this matter of longevity, a life-span of more than a thousand years is considered the normal life-expectancy of the average inhabitant of the Red Planet. Their skins are red, their eyes generally lustrous black, and their hair of the same shade. In these respects they resemble the American Indians of my native world, but their features are regular and they are, virtually all of them, a remarkably handsome race.

The city of Zorad in which I began my second life is ancient beyond the dreams of Babylon or Tyre. Here once flourished a magnificent civilization ages before those splendid and imperial cities of earthly antiquity were so much as a cluster of crude mud huts built beside the Tigris or Euphrates by primitive men barely emerged as yet from the red murk of savagery. Indeed, from the evidence of the crumbling and long-deserted quays in the oldest, by now abandoned, quarter of my natal city, where once the stately galleons rode at anchor on the restless waves of the lost seas, when Mars was young and fertile, it may be assumed that Zorad was but newly built at least a million years ago.

Into this city I was born and the name of Jad Tedron was bestowed upon me by my proud parents. My station in life in this second existence is considerably more fortunate than in my first, for I was the only son of Jugundus Jad, the jeddak or king of Zorad, and his presumed and eventual heir.

As the Prince of Zorad and heir to the throne I was raised in surroundings of the most luxurious splendor, my every need or whim satisfied by a host of attendants. My tutors were the most learned and accomplished savants of which Zorad could boast, and they instilled into my young mind all that they retained of the arts and sciences of our ancient civilization, until I became almost as conversant as they in the practice of each skill or subject.

But Barsoom, as I have said, is an ancient and dying world whose resources are dwindling away, year by year, century by century, age by age. Few are the remnants which survive of that splendid and glorious civilization which once, in the planet’s youth, spanned the globe, and those few nations which linger on must struggle ceaselessly against one another for the necessities by which to sustain their survival. Thus it is that Mars, which by an odd coincidence was named on my native world for the God of War, is a world of unceasing warfare, where every nation is at eternal and unending enmity with every other, and each of the cities of the dominant red race into which I was born are constantly at war against the ferocious and indomitable hordes of savage and pitiless green men who roam the dead seabottoms in vast numbers and pose a constant threat to the lingering remnants of the more advanced and civilized red race.

Thus I was tutored in the arts of war as well as in the arts of peace, for someday when my sire, Jugundus Jad, could no longer sustain his place and departed upon that last, melancholy pilgrimage down the River Iss to that mysterious paradise the priests of Mars believe to lie in the Valley Doron the fabled shores of the Lost Sea of Korus, I must be prepared to take his place at the head of the fighting-men of Zorad, and be ready to defend our homeland against its enemies. In preparation for that day when I would become Jad Tedron, jeddak of Zorad, I was trained virtually from the cradle in the use of longsword and rapier, in the skills of marksmanship with the terrible radium rifles and pistols which have come down to us from earlier aeons and the secret of whose manufacture has long since been lost, at least in those cities which stand yet in the dead seabottoms of the lost sea of Xanthus, and in the use of yet other weapons with whose descriptions I shall not bore him who reads this account.

I became proficient, as well, in the piloting and navigation of the remarkable aircraft employed by the dominant red peoples of Barsoom. These extraordinary vessels (which are known by a word in the universal language spoken across the length and breadth of the Red Planet which translates into English as "fliers") are the most surprising and impressive of the few surviving relics of the lost scientific achievements of the ages which preceded our own. In brief, these vehicles, which vary in size from tiny, two-man scouts to gigantic aerial dreadnaughts as huge as earthly battleships, are propelled through the thinning atmosphere of Mars by powerful radium engines. But the element which renders these skyboаts truly astonishing, especially to a former aviator accustomed to rickety, flimsy aircraft little stronger than paper kites, is that they are entirely fabricated from a light, durable metal unknown to earthly science. It is difficult to imagine any engine powerful enough to lift an airship of solid metal, even one upon a world with as light a gravity as Mars, but in this skill the Martians are assisted by their possession of an advanced scientific discovery yet denied to the savants and inventors of my native world.

This discovery is concerned with the several properties of light. The savants of Mars have, thus far, ascertained that any beam of light, whether emanating from the sun or any other source, is divisible into individual "rays," each of which has different properties. Nine such divisions of light are at this time known to the savants of Mars— in fact, it is due to the remarkable properties of the ninth ray itself that the Martians are able to sustain and replenish their dwindling atmosphere. By utilization of the first ray they power their machines; by use of the second, they heat their homes, while the third ray provides illumination for their cities and the edifices which compose them. The eighth ray provides them with the mysterious ability of levitation, for the airships of Mars are weightless as a cloud, although constructed, as I have already said, of solid metal. For their science is able to produce and store the radiations derived from this eighth solar ray in buoyancy tanks which have the amazing inherent power to reduce the metal fliers to a degree of weightlessness only achieved on my native world by dirigibles and balloons filled with hydrogen or helium gas. A slight variation in their use of the eighth ray of light enables them to use it to propel their fliers through the atmosphere at speeds which would have amazed the aviators of Earth in my time.

The sixth ray is perhaps most incredible of all. By its power their projectors are enabled to dissolve matter into nothingness—a veritable death-ray such as those dreamed of by our earthly fantasists.

And thus it was that my second youth was spent in acquiring a knowledge of the arts and sciences of peace, and in training with the weapons and instruments of war. In both departments of life I achieved a degree of proficiency which was considered highly admirable by my tutors, if I may acknowledge the fact without accusations of vanity by my reader.

Having narrated this cursory account of my birth and youth and schooling, it is not my intention to burden these pages with a more fully detailed description of the education of a Prince of Mars. Suffice it to say that my youth was spent in surroundings of palatial elegance and that I enjoyed every civilized luxury that the condition of royalty affords, and gained considerable competence in the use of weapons and the piloting of skycraft.

I cannot recall a time when I was not fully cognizant of my former life upon the planet Earth. The knowledge of this first life was with me from earliest infancy, and, in my ignorance, I supposed my acquaintance with my former incarnation to be the general rule. Often, as a child, I must have occasioned severe alarm and consternation to my parents and tutors by my innocent and childish prattle of the details of a strange life upon an alien world, which may indeed have given them cause to fear for my mental stability.

Gradually, I learned to keep silent on these matters, for it was borne home to me by a thousand curious questions and puzzled glances that my knowledge of the experiences of a prior life upon a remote and unknown world were unique to the experience of those around me. At length I learned to guard my tongue, and spoke no more of animals who went about on four legs, rather than six or eight as is common with the beasts of Mars, and on fields of unlikely emerald green rather than the scarlet sward of the rare Barsoomian forests or the ochre moss which clothes the dead seabottoms. Doubtless, as I ceased troubling them with unguarded reminiscences of another life, my elders were vastly relieved and anxious to assign these uncanny “memories” of mine to the results of an overactive imagination, rather than to an unsteady grip upon sanity itself.

But never did I allow myself to forget the weird and inexplicable enigma of my former life, and when as a youth I peered through the mighty telescopes employed by the Martian astronomers, and saw again the green fields and blue hills and shining seas of the distant planet whereon I had lived my first life, it was with a sensation of nostalgia which no words of mine are potent enough to describe. And there lived ever in the mind of Jad Tedron, Prince of Zorad, as there lives to this day, the mind and memory of Thad Dexter, the vagabond pilot who had dreamed of traveling widely and of seeing strange, far-off lands and peoples.

Well, those dreams have certainly come true, for unto Thad Dexter it had been given by a mysterious and inscrutable Fate to travel further, by some forty-three million miles, than any adventurer or explorer Earth has ever borne to my knowledge, and to visit stranger lands and peoples than any that Columbus or Marco Polo ever knew.

It was in the spirit of this that I surreptitiously experimented with and trained my innate telepathic abilities, and I believe that I have honed to an acute degree the power to project my thought through space far beyond the point which any other denizen of the Red Planet has ever, or ever will, attain. In the thought that it behooves me to impart some knowledge of my discoveries on the planet Mars for the edification of my fellow Earthlings, I have striven to the very limits of my telepathic talent to transmit to the distant world of my birth this very narrative of my adventures.

I cannot know, I shall never know, whether my thought-waves have journeyed intact across the gulf of so many millions of miles of space, or whether they have been received by a terrestrial intelligence sensitive to their wavelength. Nor, for that matter, having been received, if they have ever been recorded or preserved in any manner. For it is easy for me to imagine how natural it would be for an earthly mind to dismiss this narrative of incredible marvels and mysteries upon a weird and alien world as the hysteric phantasies of a disordered brain, or the feverish inventions of sheer imagination, or the incomprehensible fruit of nightmare, or the ravings of a lunatic.

Perhaps these telepathic communications which I now, with infinite concentration, project into the void are lost between the worlds, to disperse in the depths of interplanetary space. But it pleases me to dream that my thought-waves have impinged upon an intelligence capable of their reception and not hostile to their message; an intelligence, it may be, willing to recognize the transcendent significance of the information that human life dwells among the age-old cities and dead seabottoms of a remote world, and that humanity is not alone in the breath-taking immensity of infinite and unknown space.

Only you, who read these words, if indeed you read them at all, can ever know the reality of this, my dream.

Chapter II

The Palace of Perfection

As I have stated, I do not mean to bore my reader with a lengthy account of my birth and youth and education on Mars. This is, in part, because, from my way of thinking, my life on this planet up to my twenty-first year was only a prelude to the magnificent adventures into which Fate soon thereafter thrust me, and all that I had experienced before that fateful day was merely a preparation for what was to come.

The date whereof I speak was the thirteenth day of the Month of Thaad, which was the third month in the Martian calendar. It has lingered in my mind for so long primarily for two reasons, the second and lesser of which is that, as this day fell on the last day of one of the Martian weeks, it was thus virtually identical to “Friday the thirteenth,” a date popularly supposed by Earth superstition to be unlucky.

For me, however, it proved an occasion of supreme good fortune, for it was upon that day that my eyes first beheld the incomparable loveliness of Xana of Kanator. And that day I count as the true beginning of my second life.

A Prince of Mars must fulfill many social duties and must often attend ceremonies or social functions he would otherwise have no cause at which to be present. It is much the same with the royalty of my native world, whose position obliges them to lay cornerstones or christen battleships, which are not to be found in the general run of social events which a Duke or a Princess might be expected, by natural inclination, to desire to attend.

As a Prince of the ancient and royal house of Jad I was, therefore, frequently called upon to visit many functions of a purely ceremonial nature. One of these obligations, which either I or my father the jeddak were by custom and tradition expected to fulfill, was to attend the opening to the public of what the Zoradians call “the Palace of Perfection.” This edifice is much in the nature of a museum or a national gallery: therein are preserved every artifact surviving from the days of our ancestors which were considered to have attained artistic perfection. Sometimes the artworks housed therein are the productions of antiquity, such as statues or medallions or tapestries or painted frescoes salvaged from the oblivion that has devoured so many of the great Barsoomian cities. But sometimes—and this is extraordinarily rare—the productions of a living painter or sculptor are esteemed so highly as to merit them the supreme accolade of being placed in the spacious halls of the Palace of Perfection among the sublime achievements of ancient genius.

During the first months of the Martian year, it was the immemorial custom of Zorad to close this museum of the arts and to forbid public attendance while the many exhibits and displays were cleaned or refurbished with exquisite care by master artisans employed for that task. It was during this interval that the works of contemporary artists which had survived the scrutiny of a panel of judges composed of connoisseurs of the arts, and had been deemed worthy of comparison with the masterpieces of the past, were installed in the halls and rotundae of the immense, rambling structure. At the terminus of this period of closure, the Palace was again thrown open to the public in a formal ceremony, over which, as I have just mentioned, either I or my royal sire were expected to preside.

On this particular occasion, as chance would have it, my father was otherwise occupied with a council on military affairs. The savage green horde of Zarkol, who roamed the dead seabottoms of the mighty Xanthus, amidst the which our own city arose, were reported by an air scout in the sky navy of Zorad to be on the move. Customarily, this horde inhabits one of the many dead cities which litter the face of the Red World, abandoned ages since by our ancestors. It is the city of Zarkol, whencefrom the horde of Druj Morvath, their jeddak, derive their name.

This matter, which might portend a serious threat to the safety of the nation, precluded the jeddak from his merely formal attendance at the opening ceremonies, and I was dispatched from the Palace of a Thousand Jeddaks to take his place.

I recall that it was just before the noon hour of the Martian day that I rode forth from the palace of my fathers by the Gate of the Banths, attended by the officers and gentlemen of my retinue and their equerries.

We were dressed in our ceremonial regalia, and our leather trappings were resplendent with flashing gems and adornments of precious metals, while brightly colored pennons fluttered from the lanceheads borne by my retinue, charged with the colors not only of Zorad itself, but of my own personal ensign.

Crossing the vast plaza upon which the Palace of a Thousand Jeddaks affronts, we loped down a broad stone-paved boulevard lined to either side with immense, flowering pimalia trees, known as the Avenue of Victories from the monuments erected at intervals along the way in commemoration of ancient battles wherefrom the legions of Zorad had emerged to bear away the laurels in triumph over their enemies. It was a brave and splendid sight, the broad boulevard thronged with handsome men and women who waved and cheered as we went padding by on our restive, high-tempered thoаts. Carpets or awanings in a variety of brilliant hues adorned the carven facades of the noble mansions of the several aristocratic houses of the realm which stood in an imposing row along the way. From rooftop and dome and spire, heraldic banners fluttered in the brisk breeze, charged with a thousand bold blazonries.

Arriving at the Square of the Monuments, upon which the museum-gallery faced, we dismounted smartly, leaving our steeds in the hands of the equerries, and entered this vast temple reared to the genius of men, through gates carven in a remote epoch with the stern and frowning visages of jeddaks and jeddaras whose very names were forgotten ages ago. We were greeted within the central rotunda by a respectable crowd of citizenry, led by the officials and curators of the museum in their ceremonial finery.

“Be you welcome in this palace dedicated to the arts, O my Prince!” declared the seniormost of the curators with a humble bow, which I politely returned, murmuring some stilted formal courtesy decreed by custom from of old.

I will not burden this narrative with an elaborate account of the rituals which followed. They were soon concluded, suffice it to say, and I believe that therein I played my part in a manner befitting the solemnity of the occasion. It would have been discourteous of me to have left the building at the moment my official duties were concluded; thus, gentility suggested that I should spend a little while strolling about the vast domed hall to view and admire the several new acquisitions on exhibition for the first time, before taking my departure .

I thank whatever gods may be that I did so!

For, hardly had I so much as begun my perfunctory circuit of the rotunda, before I paused in front of a large, jewel-bright painting as if thunderstruck. The involuntary gasp of amazement this masterpiece wrung from my lips must have been clearly audible to all who stood within the great room. Aware that I had drawn all eyes to me I laughed lightly, dissembling my awe behind a flimsy pretense of aesthetic pleasure.

It was the portrait of a young woman of such incomparable beauty as I had never heretofore imagined the human features could attain to, nor the brush of an artist express upon his canvas. Her face was an exquisite oval cameo, poised upon a proud and graceful and slender neck, her features delicately chiseled, her great eyes lustrous as black jewels. Her abundant masses of glistening hair, black as a raven’s wing, were confined by a gemmed tiara of bizarre design which encircled her brows, and from the starry crest of this coronet there soared a rare single curved plume, shimmering with the peacock hues of bronze and emerald and metallic azure.

Her complexion was clear and flawless, the warm tint of ruddy copper, glowing with the rich carmine of her dimpled cheeks, and her full, perfect lips shimmered like polished rubies. Her raiment consisted of a silken scarf of lucent gossamer through which the lines of her splendid figure could be ascertained. This crossed over one gleaming shoulder and then wrapped itself about her slender, rounded upper body, leaving bare, as is the custom with the women of Mars, her perfect breasts which were, however, partially but discreetly veiled by thin chains of precious metals and narrow necklaces of glittering gems. It was the expression in that radiant and exquisite face which rendered the portrait more than merely an admirable technical achievement. For the hand of the painter had somehow caught the living spirit of his unknown model—the radiant health, the roguish humor of her voluptuous yet playful smile, the fresh, exciting vigor and zest for life legible in her vivacious, laughing eyes—and rendered them immortal, preserved by the brush of genius for all the ages to come.

I stood before this miracle of art as one entranced, devouring with my eyes the laughing, vivid beauty of this young and delicious creature. Rapt as I was, and all but oblivious to my surroundings, I was aware that my fascinated attention to this one painting was drawing curious stares in my direction, and that puzzled whispers were arising from my audience.

A tactful young lieutenant in my retinue, Rad Komis by name, noticing that my peculiar behavior was attracting attention, cleared his throat behind me.

“An admirable work, is it not, my Prince?” he murmured.

“Oh, admirable, admirable,” I said in what I hoped was an offhand manner. “Whose work is this?”

Rad Komis consulted a leaflet in which the new exhibits were listed.

“An artist named Quindus Varro. I have heard of him; a genius, but somewhat eccentric. He lives in a half-ruined villa beyond the city, eschewing the companionship of his fellow men. The painting is entitled ‘Xana of Kanator’ ”

“Indeed?” I said, pretending polite indifference. “An excellent skill. Let us pass on to observe the other artworks.” But upon the tablets of my memory I engraved the name of the artist and that of his exquisite subject.

Early that evening after a light repast in my suite I repaired to the airship hangar atop the roof of the palace, cast off the mooring lines, and took to the skies in my private scout.

The villa in which the eccentric artist, Quindus Varro, made his abode lay directly north of Zorad, beyond those waterfront precincts of the city which had become abandoned with the lessening of the population over many ages.

Silent and swift as a hovering shadow, my flier skimmed above the spires of crumbling palaces and deserted piles of ruined masonry long given over to the stealthy scavengers of the fungus forest which mantled the hills to the north and east of Zorad. The night was clear and brilliant with stars, and as both of the twin moons of Mars were aloft at this hour, their doubled moonlight transformed the nocturnal landscape into a scene of weird and romantic grandeur. The Martians call the lesser of the twin moons, which Earthlings know as Deimos, by the name of Cluros; while it is much closer to the surface of Mars than is the satellite of my native world, it revolves so slowly that it requires thirty hours and a trifle more to make one complete circuit of the planet. The greater of the two moons, which we call Phobos, the Martians know as Thuria. It soars at a height of only some five thousand miles above the surface of the planet, and completes one circumnavigation of Mars every seven and one-half hours, presenting to the eye the semblance of an immense, luminous meteor hurtling across the heavens from horizon to horizon two or three times each night.

The villa of Quindus Varro was one of the numerous edifices of antiquity which survive virtually intact due to the remarkable preservative qualities of the Martian atmosphere. The facade of this imposing structure was a colonnade composed of marble pillars, of which two were fallen; the remainder served to support a grand architrave whereon were sculptured with deathless skill the noble and graceful and heroic forms of men and women. The upper works presented a rich surface of ornament, heavy with carven faces of allegorical figures, some adorned with noble metals or precious stones. Only the east wing of this palatial edifice was slumping into decay; the remainder of the structure displayed a remarkable degree of preservation.

I brought my flier down to the courtyard before the colonnade, where slabs of marble lay tumbled about and overgrown with quantities of indigo moss. Tethering the mooring line to the capital of a fallen column, which lay mouldering amidst the rank and untamed growth, I strode up a flight of broken stone steps to discover the towering doors of the portal widely ajar. Within I found a circular rotunda whose marble floor was littered with dead vegetation and matted with indescribable filth. The many-colored moonlight fell in glorious shafts through broken clerestory windows to illuminate walls of gleaming alabaster, hung with tattered, faded tapestries, and to gleam along the dirty rail of a graceful stair which coiled to the second level.

A cracked, peevish voice hailed me from the darkness above.

“What noisome intruder disturbs the solitude of Quindus Varro? There is little else but garbage here to steal, if you be a thief; this, and the poor rags that clothe my body, and a few oddments of the painter's craft. Can it be that my rivals fear the genius of Quindus Varro to such an absurd extent, that they have secured the services of an assassin to forever extinguish that spark of divine fire?”

Another than an inhabitant of the Red Planet might have first suspected an uninvited intruder to be a burglar, but this is not so. On Barsoom, for some strange reason, thievery is so exceptionally rare as to be virtually unknown, and I have not the slightest reason why. It is another of the many mysteries which I cannot explain to my reader (if any shall ever peruse these words). It is almost as if stealing had never been invented by the dwellers on the Red Planet; if so, I greatly fear thievery to be the only crime or vice unique to the peoples of Earth, for the Martian civilisation enjoys, if that is the word I want, every other criminal tendency known to my former planet.

Thus addressed, I stepped into the pool of moonlight so that the man could clearly see me from above, and announced my name in a firm voice, although neglecting to state my rank in society.

“Jad Tedron, Jad Tedron,” the old man mumbled. “I know no Jad Tedron. What do you wish of me, that you must intrude your unwanted presence upon my meditations?”

I announced myself an admirer of his art, come to view such masterpieces as the portrait named “Xana of Kanator,” which I had but recently seen for the first time, and, perchance, to purchase a canvas or two, if the price did not exceed my modest means.

At the mention of my purchasing a painting, the old man warmed to something resembling good humor, and even displayed some rudimentary sense of hospitality, affably bidding me ascend to the second story where he maintained his studio, and, once I had entered, whisking dusty cloths and plaster forms from a low bench to provide me with a seat.

This Quindus Varro was a man of severely advanced years such as are seldom encountered on Mars, where a man may keep the trim, supple figure and unlined face of youth for centuries, and where by far the greater portion of inhabitants succumb to violent deaths before age wrinkles their lineaments or whitens their hirsute adornments. He was remarkably ugly, too, which further served to set him apart from the common run of humankind upon this planet, where perfection of form and beauty of features are many times more common than on my native world. For a nose he displayed a swollen proboscis whose broken veins and sanguine hue suggested an overfondness for intoxicants. His face and wattled neck were a mass of sagging wrinkles, and his seamed brow was furrowed by cares or by the years under untidy snowy locks. His rheumy eyes were sharp and keen, however, and his tongue sharper yet. And, however unkempt his gown and person, I noticed that his brushes were scrupulously clean, his pots of paint immaculate, and the various tools and implements of his art were kept in perfect condition.

“You admire my ‘Xana,’ eh, Jad Tedron! Mediocre, my dear sir; oh, charming enough for its kind, I’ll grant you; but it pales into insignificance before some of my recent work. Come, let me show you the canvas upon which I am presently at work—”

Assuming an air of polite interest mingled with indifference, my beating heart belied, I interrupted to ask if he employed living models, or worked from imagination alone.

“In the case of your ‘Xana of Kanator,’ for instance,” I finished. “Is there such a woman, and, if so, where did you find her?”

Quindus Varro shrugged peevishly. “Oh, she was a high-born lady of Kanator. I did her portrait within the year, you know. This painting upon which I am currently at work, by the way, should interest a connoisseur of your taste and discernment profoundly: the delicate use of line, the subtle balance of color—”

I disengaged myself from Quindus Varro as soon as could decently be managed, purchasing a small, superb, deftly composed miniature, for which I paid easily twice what it was worth, and returned to my flier just as the swifter of the twin moons in its rapid traversement of the sky dipped below the horizon.

My heart palpitated within my bosom; my breath came in light, fast panting. “Xana of Kanator” had a living model! And now I knew where and how to find her, which was the sole purpose which would motivate my entire existence from this point of time forward into the unknown and mysterious future . . .

Chapter III

Kar Havas, Panthan

And thus it was that a few, careless words from the lips of Quindus Varro touched a spark within me that flamed now with clear, steady, unwavering purpose.

His words had laid to rest at least two of the fears that had haunted my thoughts during the flight to his villa. The first of these was the dreadful possibility that the exquisite girl in the portrait might be an imaginary or ideal figure, painted from sheer visionary genius. But now I knew the portrait had a living model. This knowledge allayed the second fear, that which had been uppermost in my mind. I refer to the possibility that the portrait could easily have been painted many years, perhaps many centuries, before it had been hung in the Palace of Perfection. But Quindus Varro had assured me that he had painted the portrait within this same year, so Xana of Kanator, whoever she might be, must still be in the fresh bloom of that radiant loveliness which had so enchanted me.

A third fear yet gnawed within my breast. And that was that the girl of my dreams was already pledged or even wed to another. Such an eventuality was scarcely conceivable to me, for the gods could not play so cruel and despicable a trick upon one who had never knowingly offended them; still and all, the possibility existed, and I knew that I would never rest until I had proved this third of my ffars to be groundless.

During the feverish days which followed I laid my plans with care and cunning. I could not simply do as my impatient heart bid me, and fly to Kanator upon the moment to see in the flesh this entrancing creature. This was impossible for an implacable rivalry has long existed between the cities of Zorad and Kanator; the two realms, so closely similar in wealth and extent and power, are irrevocably divided by an ancient schism, and the Zoradians and the Kanatorians have been hereditary enemies for a thousand generations.

The cause of the hatred which exists between the two mightiest nations of the Xanthus plains is lost in the mists of antiquity. No one today recalls the original dispute which arose between the rival kingdoms. But the hatred exists nonetheless and is no less vehement, for that its origins are long since forgotten.

I could not, for this reason, safely enter the city of my enemies without assuming a disguise or a false identity. For nothing would delight the soul of Lorquas Zed, jeddak of Kanator, more than to discover the princely heir of his ancient foe wandering about the streets of his realm like a moonstruck lover. The moment my flier descended into the landing stages of Kanator, and the emblem of Jad Tedron, Prince of Zorad, was recognized, I would be seized and held captive, either to suffer a lingering and horrible death under the knives of the torturers, or to be held in ransom against a sum so enormous as to beggar my father’s realm, or to be restrained as a means whereby to force from him to cede to the Kanatorians vast territories, the loss of which would forever tip the balance of power between our two realms in favor of Kanator.

I resolved, therefore, to adopt a pseudonym and to enter the city of my foes disguised as a common panthan or soldier of fortune. Our cities had exchanged no embassies since the last outbreak of war between us, which had occurred some twenty years before; therefore it was highly unlikely that any citizen of Kanator would be able to recognize my features. The risk seemed to me well worth the taking, for I knew I could not rest until I had beheld the loveliness of Xana of Kanator in the flesh.

Since I could not make the flight to Kanator in my own private air yacht, which bore at prow and flanks the royal cognizance of Zorad and my own colors, I must procure an unmarked craft. The following morning I descended into the city and entered an establishment where a variety of old or second-hand craft were offered at public sale. After deliberation I settled upon a small, two-man flier of superb trim and balance, which bore no markings. Paying the purchase price on the spot, I maneuvered my new acquisition into a rooftop hangar in a remote, outlying district of the city situated far from my usual haunts, a hangar available at public rental which my aid, Rad Komis, had secured for my purposes only an hour before.

During the next two days I labored on the flier with the knowledgeable assistance of one of the aircraft mechanics who worked in the palace and who had been a trusted and loyal friend to me since childhood. We carefully battered and scarred the sleek hull, a light but durable shell of aluminum and steel, until it looked sufficiently dented and disreputable to the casual glance to pass for such a vessel as might be owned by an unemployed panthan of slender purse. We scraped several sections of the hull and works clean of the metallic grey enamel wherewith the craft was painted, and applied a subtle chemical concoction known to my helper which caused the exposed metal hull to become scabrous and scaly with rust. In no wise did we impair the trim fighting efficiency or flying speed of the snug little craft by these artistic deceptions, which were merely of a cosmetic nature.

In a similar mode to my unobtrusive purchase of the flier, I procured from yet other establishments the plain leather harness and trappings of a down-at-heels panthan, such as might be worn by a warrior of that class. For here again my own trappings and accouterments were of such princely elegance as to be well beyond my powers to disguise. I should perhaps note here that a Martian fighting-man goes nearly naked, as indeed do the inhabitants of Mars in general, regardless of sex or station. A Martian warrior wears about his loins a length of cloth which hangs down before and behind him, boots or high-laced sandals or buskins serve as his footwear, and his waist and upper torso are cinched into a number of buckled straps or leathern belts to which are affixed his weapons and ornaments.

Badges and insignia of rank or family, together with duelling trophies marking victories or kills, often of noble metals set with precious stones, are fastened to these trappings, and the leather itself may be elegantly carved with arabesques or washed in gilt or studded with gems. This suffices for clothing on a planet where there are no genuine seasonal variations in temperature, although a cloak is customarily worn.

To complete my impersonation of a poor panthan, or mercenary swordsman, I purchased trappings of plain, unornamented leather, making certain that the harness I selected was worn and frayed as if from years of actual use. I wound a loincloth of scarlet silk about my lower body, donned plain radium weapons in worn leather holsters, selected a well-crafted and beautifully balanced rapier whose hilt was of polished steel rather than gold and set with semi-precious lapis and agate rather than rare jewels, slung about my shoulders a dark, second-hand cloak of plain and serviceable cloth, and was ready to venture incognito into the city of my enemies.

The flight to Kanator was accomplished that same evening, on the fourth day following my conversation with the misanthropic painter. I had taken my lieutenant, Rad Komis, into my confidence and had divulged to him the nature and purpose of my mission, for on a thousand occasions in the past he had more than proved himself unswerving in his loyalty to me and more than worthy of my trust.

The stalwart young officer, who hailed from Vaxar, a city far to the north of Zorad amidst the Omtolian Mountains, and whose years were precisely equal to my own, considered my thus venturing even in disguise into the city of our hereditary foes a rash and foolhardy venture. This opinion did not, I noticed with warm appreciation, impede him from volunteering to share the adventure at my side; indeed, he implored me for permission to accompany me on this perilous voyage. I declined, however, for the deed was mine alone to undertake: never would it be said of Jad Tedron of Zorad that, in following the private passions of his heart, he risked the life of an honest and worthy friend.

Swearing my accomplice to secrecy, then, I departed from Zorad that evening. My flier hurtled through the skies wherein the two moons glowed like great lamps of colored fire, at a velocity which I calculated would bring me within the vicinity of Kanator shortly before sunrise. For many haads I soared effortlessly above the interminable stretches of ochre moss which carpeted the ancient and desolate barrens which once had been the floor of a primordial ocean. I chose the nocturnal hour of my departure for a triple reason: not only should I avoid chance notice in departing Zorad at this hour, but also I might thereby best elude the attentions of the merciless green hordes of Zarkol who are wont to dwell in the ruined and deserted cities which rise amidst the Xanthian plains and who traverse the dead seabottom in vast cavalcades of chariots drawn by zitidars. And also it seemed to me a good idea to enter Kanator at an hour so early that few would be abroad to observe my arrival.

The flight consumed some hours, which I spent in dreaming on the ravishing loveliness of Xana of Kanator. Some forty xats before the hour of sunrise the speed of my craft slackened and I perceived a splendid metropolis ahead of me, bathed in the glory of the hurtling moons. It was Kanator. And somewhere in that maze of majestic palaces and soaring spires dwelt the exquisite woman to whom already my heart was half given.

I descended to a lower level and entered the city from another direction, so that should any discern my arrival they would not observe me entering Kanator from the direction of Zorad. I traversed the partially collapsed walls at a speed and height and angle of flight that made my arrival as unobtrusive as possible, and descended to moor my flier in a public hangar on the rooftop of a rundown building in what seemed to be a fairly nondescript quarter of the metropolis. I was pleased to see that the attendant paid me not the slightest attention. The fellow merely accepted in the most bored and lackadaisical manner imaginable the coin I silently proffered him for the usual rental fee.

Descending to the street I located a public house and purchased a cup of wine, carefully scrutinizing the bill of fare so as to be certain of purchasing the least expensive vintage, which was in keeping with my pretense of being an unemployed panthan of lean and slender purse. No one paid me any particular notice as I sat in a dim corner, quietly nursing my drink, while thinking through the next step in my plan to find Xana of Kanator.

Fate, however, soon took a hand in the arrangement of my fortunes.

The other men in the room were an ordinary lot: disreputable loafers, seedy tradesmen, repair mechanics and lower-class working men of a variety of common occupations for the most part, probably including in their number a few petty criminals. They tended to be sullen, weary, and rather quiet on the whole—with one exception. This individual was a hulking, loudmouthed oaf, his coarse features inflamed by drink, who noisily bragged of his amatory conquests and in general made a nuisance of himself.

He had eyed me up and down in a rude, insulting manner when I first entered and quietly ordered wine, and had roughly jostled my arm as I strode past him to the grimy table. I had dismissed this as accidental on his part and thought no more of it, but soon, bored by the inattention of his dull, indifferent audience, who morosely nursed their drinks, shrugging at his boastful monologue, he let his restless and truculent little red-rimmed eyes prowl about the room in search of a readier source of amusement.

My eye caught his as he glanced about. There may have been a small smile on my lips at that moment, I cannot say. At any rate, he stiffened like a predator scenting its prey and directed a surly glare in my direction.

“What are you grinning at, fellow?” he demanded in a belligerent tone of voice. Heads craned to see whom he was addressing in this manner. I shrugged casually and mildly observed that I had not been aware of smiling.

A man may change his leather, but it is difficult to disguise his breeding. I fear my accent and diction revealed me as a man of birth and education, for the ugly oaf sneered and loudly repeated my words in an exaggerated burlesque of my refined pronunciation. This roused a few chuckles from the crowd, whereupon, basking in the applause and sensing a new victim ripe for the bullying, the man came swaggering over to where I sat and glowered down at me, his surly face heavy with menace.

“I say you’re grinning at me,” he growled. “I don’t like it when strangers who have no business in this district sit and grin at me!”

“I meant no offense. I was not even aware I smiled,” I said, careful to keep my tone of voice and the expression on my face neutral. It seemed wisest to avoid this encounter so as not to draw undue attention to myself which might give occasion for speculation as to who I was and where I had come from. But it took an effort of will for me to placate this bully with soft words when my immediate natural inclination was to rise and smash him to the floor with a single blow.

Suddenly, as is often the case with those heavily intoxicated, his manner changed like lightning. One moment he was surly and scowling; in the next he was scarlet and trembling with rage.

“On your feet when you exchange words with Curan Gor, you smoothfaced puppy!” And with those words he slapped me across the face with a savage blow of one massive hand.

All sound ceased; the room became deathly silent. In the next instant those who sat nearby unobtrusively rose to their feet and sidled away from Guran Gor and me, leaving that portion of the room empty. I sat there, pale as death, cold with fury, my face stinging from the blow. The huge man towered over me, hands hovering near the pommel of his sword. He breathed heavily between open, pendulous lips, and from time to time the tip of his tongue would snake out to wet his lips.

There was nothing to do but to fight him.

I sprang from my chair in one lithe, whip-like blur of motion. One fist I balled and drove thudding into the pit of his belly with all the strength of the steely sinews of arm and shoulder. He sagged forward, eyes goggling, and as he did so I brought a terrific uppercut from the floor. My fist caught him on the point of the jaw with an audible crack, like the sound of a sapling suddenly broken. It was a terrific blow and it lifted him an inch or two off the floor. He went floundering backwards, crashing among the tables, and lay sprawled like a dead man.

The tense, watching crowd relaxed, shuffled, eyed me with dull and wary approval, and returned to its drinks again. The man who served us wine emerged from his station wiping his hands on a scrap of dirty cloth, took up the unconscious hulk of Guran Gor by the feet and dragged him out a side door into the alley, returning to give me a passive, noncommittal look before busying himself with the serving of drinks again. The confrontation was over almost before it began, and the room returned to normal.

“I can’t help admiring the way you handled Guran Gor just now,” said a voice at my elbow. I looked up as a bony little man with the sharp, cunning eyes of a ferret came to my table.

“Thank you,” I said.

“My name is Ulvius Spome,” he said unctuously. “Let me buy you a drink and let’s get acquainted. I might have a job for a fellow who can handle himself as ably as you, but that depends on whether or not you can use a sword as well as you can use your fists.”

Shrugging, I indicated an empty chair, into which he slid, calling loudly for service. He ordered a bottle of decent vintage and sat back, examining me narrowly with a little smile on his thin lips. His eyes slid over me, weighing, measuring, calculating. I felt clammy and unclean as those cold, shrewd eyes crawled over me — it was as if they left behind a trail of slime upon my flesh.

“I am pretty good with a sword,” I said. “What kind of a job did you have in mind?”

He poured the wine with a practiced twist of the wrist.

“Easy, now, let’s get acquainted a little before we talk business. From the cut of you I would figure you for a panthan, right? And from the dismal slop you've been drinking, I’d say it’s been a long time since you worked and that you could probably use a bit of change about now, right?”

“On both counts,” I admitted.

“What’s your name, and where are you from?”

“My name is Kar Havas,” I said without a moment’s hesitation, giving the first name that came into my head. Kar Havas had been a boyhood friend of mine, killed in an accident with his flier many years before. “I am a native of Vaxar in the land of Omtol, but I have been working for some years now in Amdor,” I added, mentioning a small, insignificant city northeast of Vaxar in the eastern foothills of the mountain country.

Ulvius Spome nodded, then inquired why I had happened to leave my former place of employment.

I laughed in a self-conscious manner. “I became attached to the retinue of a noble house in Amdor, whose master was possessed by a deathly fear his rivals and enemies were planning his assassination. Actually, these enemies existed only in his fearful imagination. It was a snug and secure berth and I could have stayed there for many years to come, but my master’s wife began acting as though she found me rather attractive . . .”

Ulvius Spome sniggered. “I get it! So you flew out of there before your master put something or other in your drink, or maybe a knife between your ribs, eh?”

“Something like that,” I smiled. “Today, doubtless my former master has a new bodyguard; presumably, he chose one even uglier than himself!”

The little ferret-eyed man burst into a peal of raucous laughter, and poured more wine into my cup, before getting down to business.

It transpired that he wanted me to display my abilities with the sword be fore one Han Hova, who was gamesmaster of the great arena of Kanator and who managed the gladiatorial combats which formed the most popular sport among the citizens. These gladiatorial contests, so like the gory festivals held in the Roman Colisseum, are a depraved practice into which the Kanatorians have sunk in recent years, since their resounding defeat at the hands of Zorad in the war I have mentioned earlier. The custom of lolling on the rows of an amphitheatre while men fight to the death against savage beasts and other men for your amusement is a loathsome and bestial vice to which, among the many peoples of Barsoom, only the bestial green hordes are customarily addicted.

They are a race of cruel and fiendish monsters, devoid of the slightest trace of sentiment or mercy or friendship or love, and count little better than wild beasts in the estimate of the red Martian civilizations. To learn that Kanator had developed a thirst for these savage spectacles was a clear sign of the decadence into which she has sunken under the dynastic house of Zed. For, while we Zoradians delight in contests of skill between trained swordsmen, and in air races and similar contests between teams of thoat-trawn chariots, we hold in the utmost abhorrence the very concept that a battle to the death between brave men is even to be considered a form of entertainment.

This being the case, my gorge rose at the thought of partaking in such disgusting spectacles, and would have curtly declined had it not occurred to me that if the citizenry attended these games in such vast numbers as Ulvius Spome swore was so, I might find it far easier in this way to discover the whereabouts of Xana of Kanator. And besides, as I was accounted among my fellow-Zoradians a swordsman of superlative skill, it seemed very likely that I should have little or naught to fear as regards the safety of my person during such combats as might ensue in the games.

Therefore, I decided to tentatively accept the offer of Ulvius Spome, although I distrusted his motives and did not in the least like his appearance. We promptly made an appointment to meet at the gates of the great arena of Kanator the following morning, where he promised to arrange for me to display my swordsmanship before the eyes of this Han Hova.

SYNOPSIS

I envision a series of at least three books, perhaps five, laid on the Barsoom of Edgar Rice Burroughs, but involving none of the characters or settings used in his famous novels.

On page 23 of Chessmen of Mars, Burroughs states that the region northwest of Helium is one of the least-known areas of the planet. It is completely unknown to the Heliumites, who have never ventured into those parts. I have chosen this, the Xanthus, region as the setting of my new Mars books, so as to avoid employing any of the cities or regions used by Burroughs.

And, since the Heliumites know nothing of the Xanthus region, the inhabitants of the Xanthus region can know nothing of Helium or the other southern cities. In this way, I can avoid using or even mentioning by name any of the characters invented by Burroughs.

The only place-names of his invention which appear in these projected books will be the name Barsoom itself, and the names of the two moons. Without exception, all other place or personal names are of my own coinage, although done, of course, closely in line with the Burroughsian style of names.

This should defuse the Estate from any legal action, since nobody can possibly own an imaginary place or invented combinations of letters such as “thoat” or “jeddak.”

After the events described in the three opening chapters of the first book, Jad Tedron displays his sword-skills before the gamesmaster, and demonstrates his prowess in the arena for the next few days. During these days, panthans and vagabond warriors display their skills before the throng, hoping for employment. Jad Tedron secures sleeping quarters in a public house and moors his flier on its rooftop hangar facilities. Ulvius Spome receives his commission for recruiting Jad Tedron from the gamesmaster, and tries to insinuate himself into closer friendship with Tedron but is repulsed.

Walking home from the games one evening, Tedron surprises three masked assassins attacking a lone man, and goes to aid him. He slays one of the assassins and drives the others off, but is slightly wounded in the fray. The man he rescued, Ptol Kovus, is a member of the noble House of Ptol; he takes Tedron home and sees that his wounds are tended to. Since he fears assassination, having made a powerful enemy concerning whom he tells Tedron little, he hires the panthan on the spot as a bodyguard. Tedron rightly feels it would be contrary to the role he is playing to decline employment, and reluctantly accepts.

A few days later, accompanying Ptol Kovus at a glittering social function, he is first lifted into the heights of bliss and then dashed into the depths of despair, when he encounters the lovely Xana of Kanatov face to face, only in the next instant to see Ptol Kovus step forward and embrace and kiss the girl. He later learns that she is the sister of his employer and is being wooed by Zed Tonus, the handsome son of the jeddak of Kanator, Lorquas Zed.

He soon learns that the Ptolian house is a rival for the dais of Kanator and that Zed Tomus desires to take Xana for his mate and destroy her father and brother—the assassins, therefore, conspire not only against Ptol Kovus, but the entire Ptolian family. One night he is awakened by a slight sound and peers from the window to see an unmarked flier, its running-lights muffled, hovering about the upper tiers of the Ptolian palace. As he watches, a wrapped, struggling figure is borne into the craft. At the last possible moment, a ray of moonlight illuminates the features of the captive and her captor— and discovers that Xana of Kanator is being carried off by Zed Tomus!

Jad Tedron mounts his own flier and hurtles in pursuit. His engine is pierced by a projectile from the radium rifles of Zed Tomus’ hirelings, however, and the craft floats idly above the dead seabottom, rendering further pursuit impossible. Eventually, with dawn, it drifts over one of the dead cities which litter the plains of Xanthus, and Tedron manages to secure the mooring line to the crest of a tower, descending thereby to the street. Searching for food and drink, he discovers one of the gigantic green Martian warriors chained helplessly to a stone pillar, perishing slowly from hunger and thirst. A cruel enemy has left covered dishes of food and drink, and also the weapons and trappings of the hordesman, in tempting view, but just out of reach.

This revolts the chivalry of Tedron’s earthborn soul and he cautiously gives food and drink to the chained warrior, a chieftain of the Zarkol horde named Zandus Zan, waylaid and bludgeoned into insensibility, then chained and left to suffer a cruel, slow death by his fiendish jeddak, Druj Morvath, who fears his prowess and his popularity among the warriors of the Zarkol horde as a potential rival for the dais.

The red and green Martians are implacable racial foes, but as each needs something from the other, they devise a temporary truce. Zandus Zan agrees to this unheard-of notion because, being coldly emotionless, the green Martians obey strict logic, and since to decline the truce means slow death, it is only the argument of pure reason that he accept the truce, since it is better to live than to die.

Zandus Zan informs Tedron of the whereabouts of his wrecked flier, wherefrom Tedron extracts the tools required to repair his motors. He then places the keys to the chains which bind the gigantic warrior within reach, after cautiously freeing one hand from its bonds and prudently hiding the hordeaman,s weapons in one of the ruined buildings nearby.

He ascends to his flier and, works at repairing the engines, having warily severed the mooring-line so that the green warrior cannot attack him once his back is turned. He flies off, leaving Zandus Zan to his own devices.

Meanwhile Xana, having cut herself free with the small knife every red Martian woman wears concealed upon her person to protect her chastity, swings down the anchor-cable, dropping lightly to the sward. With relief, she watches as the flier of Zed Tomus soars on, dwindling from sight. She finds, with dawn, a forested region not uncommon in these northerly parts, and is seeking nourishment when attacked by a huge banth, or Barsoomian lion.

Zed Tomus eventually discovers that Xana is missing, and searches the dead seabottom for some trace of her. Hi finds an unknown city in the Omtolian mountains and is forced to land by two heavily armed patrol fliers. He finds himself a captive in the city of Horah, where a race of listless slaves are ruled by a despotic madman. The mad jeddak is called Nad Puvus and is—or claims to be—over one million years old. He exists in the form of a bodiless head which is attached to pumps and tanks by tubes which circulate fresh blood into his severed head. He controls this race of frightened, will-less slaves by terrific hypnotic powers, and a small cadre of hardened warriors by promises of eternal life in a mode similar to his own.

Xana is rescued from the banth by savage green warriors of the Zarkol horde, and is carried a captive into the dead city of Zarkol where Druj Morvath reigns. He is a huge, bloated, corpulent, and hideously disfigured ogre and Xana knows her life will be the nadir of misery under his mastery. But the warrior who rescued her from the banth is none other than Zandus Zan, who has returned to Zarkol saying nothing of the treachery of Druj Morvath, who dares not reveal before his own chieftains his crime against their champion. On pure whim, because in an unguarded moment Xana yearns aloud for the protection of Jad Tedron, Zandus Zan opposes his jeddak’s claim to the girl, claiming her as his own slave, since he took her captive in the first place. Druj Morvath dares not deny his right to the slave, although nursing in his cunning and sadistic brain yet another motive for the destruction of Zandus Zan.

In this and the successive novels of the trilogy we follow the wanderings and adventures of Jad Tedron as he searches for and then finds Xana of Kanator, slowly teaches the pitiless green chieftain, Zandus Zan, that the softer emotions such as gratitude and friendship (despised as weaknesses by the green men) are not totally devoid of worth or meaning.

In the second novel of this sequence, Mystery Men of Mars, our hero and heroine penetrate to a previously unknown underground ocean beneath the Martian surface, called the Forgotten Sea of Korus, where survive among fantastically lush prehistoric vegetation astounding survivals of early Martian life in the form of savage, undomesticated proto-thoats, enormous insectlike [creatures], a host of deadly reptiles almost extinct upon the surface, and a previously unknown race of blue Martians who rule the subterranean ocean in gigantic floating raft-cities.

The blue men sought refuge in the cavern-world a million years ago, as the surface began to die. Now they believe themselves the only living Martians and it is an article of their faith that the surface is not only devoid of life but permanently uninhabitable. They cannot account for the existence of the red Martians they have taken captive, and thus, with a paranoia long inbred, consider them phantoms and ignore their presence.

In the third novel, Goddess of Mars, flying in pursuit of Zad Tomus, who has again captured and carried off his beloved Xana of Kanator, Jad Tedron discovers a city inhabited by people called Azors, who consider themselves of divine lineage as the descendants of Azor Adz, a divinity they believe to inhabit the moon Cluros, and a female divinity, the spirit of the moon Thuria. They are ruled by a gorgeous woman as their jeddara and goddess, Azara, whom they call Daughter of the Two Moons. She conceives of a violent passion for Jad Tedron and would make him her consort, only to be coldly refused, which, of course, leads to his imprisonment in the pits and a succession of adventures.

The climax of the series, or at least of the trilogy, comes when having disposed of their foes, Jad Tedron and Xana are flying back to Zorad, only to discover that in their absence her father has overthrown the jealous jeddak, becoming jeddak in his place, while Jugundus Jad, Tedron's mighty sire, learning that his son has ventured alone into the stronghold of his hereditary enemies, and becoming alarmed at his prolonged absence, directs his war fleet against the neighboring city. The two hosts are drawn up for battle when Jad and Xana fly into their midst. From the debacle they are saved by the arrival of the Zarkol horde, and it is Zandus Zan who mediates their dispute peacefully—if only to prove that even a coldly emotionless, cruel and pitiless green warrior can be sensible of such weak emotions as gratitude and the repaying of friendship.

If a fourth novel is desired (or more), the next book will be The Wizard of Mars and will concern itself with a great, if deranged, Martian scientist named Ulthan Ptome whose genius has led him to the discovery of two unknown forms of energy, the tenth and the eleventh "rays" of light, even as his madness has goaded him into declaring himself the emperor of all Mars, which he intends to conquer by reducing every city which opposes his regime to powder before the ferocity of his energy weapons.

A fifth novel might concern itself with a race of warrior women who have sworn undying enmity to all males—Amazons of Mars.

As the territory is sufficiently vast and the active characters sufficiently numerous, the series could, if desired, be indefinitely extended by the continuous introduction of new settings and plot-elements.

But, as of now, I am interested in obtaining a three-book contract for A Swordsman of Mars, The Mystery Men of Mars, and Goddess of Mars.